<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../input-cache/schemas/R5/fhir-single.xsd">
    <a name="top" />
    <h3>Initial Diagnosis and Monitoring Workflow</h3>

    <img height="500" src="flow-initial-diagnosis.png" alt="Initial Diagnosis and Monitoring Workflow diagram"/>

    <p>When the patient first accesses the tool, it will check to see if that patient has an existing diagnosis of hypertension. If the patient does, the tool will proceed through the monitoring &amp; treatment pathway. If the patient has not been diagnosed, the tool will check how many blood pressure measurements the patient has within the last 2 years. If a full set (4 office, 6 home, or 12 ambulatory measurements) does not exist for the patient, the tool will recommend home blood pressure monitoring be used to obtain additional measurements.</p>

    <p>If a set of measurements exists, the tool will evaluate the set. If the mean value of the set OR of all recorded blood pressures is > 140 SBP or > 90 DBP, the tool will recommend diagnosis with stage 2 hypertension, assigning greater likelihood of diagnosis if average of blood pressures or all recorded blood pressures are > 160 DBP.</p>

    <p>If blood pressure set average is not > 140 SBP or >90 DBP, the tool will assess the likelihood of stage 1 hypertension. If the most recent blood pressure set averages >130/80, the tool will suggest diagnosis of stage 1 hypertension. If the average of all blood pressure readings is >130/80, the tool will recommend the use of home or ambulatory blood pressure monitoring to collect more readings. This will proceed to the monitoring and treatment pathway.</p>

    <p>If the blood pressure average is not >130/80, but high variability exists, the tool will recommend the use of ambulatory blood pressure monitoring. Blood pressure variability is independently predictive of poor outcomes; however, due to the significant measurement inaccuracies from both home and office blood measurement in practice, much blood pressure variability is due to this measurement error. In addition, the effects of blood pressure variability are most significant over the long term, with mixed evidence over the short and medium term. Thus, we set the threshold for the identification of variability at a very high level - > a standard deviation of > 11 mmHg. This level is the most associated with poor outcomes. Removing this criterion or changing the language may be useful for some groups to model their local clinical needs.  See Stevens SL, Wood S, Koshiaris C, Law K, Glasziou P, Stevens RJ, McManus RJ. Blood pressure variability and cardiovascular disease: systematic review and meta-analysis. BMJ. 2016 Aug 9;354:i4098. doi: 10.1136/bmj.i4098. PMID: 27511067; PMCID: PMC4979357 for details.</p>

    <p>This will proceed to the monitoring and treatment pathway.</p>

    <a name="links" />
    <h3>Links</h3>
    <ul>
        <li><a href="https://www.cdc.gov/bloodpressure/measure.htm">CDC: How to measure blood pressure</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://www.heart.org/en/health-topics/high-blood-pressure/understanding-blood-pressure-readings">AHA: Understanding High Blood Pressure Readings</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://www.heart.org/en/health-topics/high-blood-pressure/understanding-blood-pressure-readings/monitoring-your-blood-pressure-at-home">AHA: Monitoring your blood pressure at home</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://my.clevelandclinic.org/health/diagnostics/16330-24-hour-ambulatory-blood-pressure-monitoring">Cleveland Clinic: 24-hour ambulatory blood pressure monitoring</a></li>
    </ul>
</div>
