<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../input-cache/schemas/R5/fhir-single.xsd">
    <p>
        The following flowcharts represent the decision logic we developed from a review of 71 Hypertension recommendations
        taken from 8 different guidelines (per Alper et al.). Of these 71 recommendations, 42 have agreement between multiple
        guidelines. Any recommendation that was disagreed upon by direction (recommended to use in treatment versus recommended
        NOT to use in treatment) was excluded from this logic. All recommendations that were disagreed upon by strength of
        recommendation (weak "for" vs strong "for") are included in this logic, but output indicates users should "consider"
        as a care option rather than "recommend" as a course of action.
    </p>
    <h3>Definitions</h3>
    <p>The decision logic for all workflows contains some common concepts defined in this section.</p>
    <h4>Blood Pressure readings</h4>
    <p>Workflow logic referring to "all" BP readings refers to all readings taken in the previous 2 years.
      Blood Pressure observations must be in the ValueSet
      <a href="http://cts.nlm.nih.gov/fhir/ValueSet/2.16.840.1.113883.3.600.2012">http://cts.nlm.nih.gov/fhir/ValueSet/2.16.840.1.113883.3.600.2012</a>
      and must have a unit mm[Hg] and a status of 'final', 'amended', or 'corrected'.
    </p>
    <p>
      A BP observation is considered to be a home reading if BPObservation.extension value contains a measurementSetting with SNOMED Code ‘264362003’.
      Otherwise, it is considered an office reading. In practice, there were challenges getting ambulatory monitoring procedures for blood pressure
      from a real FHIR implementation so ambulatory observations are not currently considered.
    </p>
    <h4>Last Set of Blood Pressure readings</h4>
    <p>
      In order to generate useful recommendations, the decision support system needs to have a minimum number of blood pressure
      readings taken over the last 2 years to be used as the most recent "set" of BPs in several calculations. The initial approach
      was to require at least 12 hours of ambulatory readings, 4 office readings, or 6 home readings to establish the set and to prioritize
      which set was used based on the presumed accuracy of the source (Ambulatory > Office > Home). But different types
      of readings may be interspersed throughout the 2 year period, potentially leading to more recent readings being discarded from
      analysis if they weren't part of the prioritized set.
    </p>

    <p>
      To avoid these pitfalls, a point system is employed to define the most recent BP set. Each blood pressure reading is assigned points as follows:
    </p>
    <ul>
      <li>Office observation = 1 point</li>
      <li>Home observation = .667 points</li>
    </ul>

    <p>
      A patient must have at least <strong>4 points</strong> total in observations from the last 2 years to have a set. And the most recent BP set would be the minimum number of
      most recent readings that add up to 4. In the example below, the most recent 4 home and 2 office readings would be used:
    </p>
    <img height="300" src="bp-set.png" alt="BP Set Calculation Example" style="margin-bottom:10px;"/>
    <h4>Blood Pressure Variability</h4>
    <p>If a set of blood pressure observations is found, systolic readings for the last 2 years are also checked for high variability.
      If the standard deviation of systolic readings is > 11, a recommendation for ambulatory monitoring is provided.
    </p>
    <h4>Qualifying Blood Pressure Goal</h4>
    <p>
      Many of the recommendations are generated by comparing the patient's current blood pressure to their stated blood pressure goal.
      Implementers may want to create a default Goal for the patient if one does not already exist so that these recommendations fire.
      The goal must have a lifecyleStatus in ('proposed', 'planned', 'accepted', 'active', 'completed').
      The goal should have a single target, with one measure in the ValueSet for Systolic Blood Pressure
      (<a href="http://cts.nlm.nih.gov/fhir/ValueSet/2.16.840.1.113762.1.4.1104.2">http://cts.nlm.nih.gov/fhir/ValueSet/2.16.840.1.113762.1.4.1104.2</a>) and one measure
      in the Value Set for Diastolic Blood Pressure (<a ref="http://cts.nlm.nih.gov/fhir/ValueSet/2.16.840.1.113883.3.526.2.1045">http://cts.nlm.nih.gov/fhir/ValueSet/2.16.840.1.113883.3.526.2.1045</a>).
      Both measures must have detail that is a quantity with unit mm[Hg].
    </p>
    <h4>Patient "On Track" to Reach Blood Pressure Goal</h4>
    <p>Usually, a patient with high blood pressure will receive recommendations for lifestyle changes first and will only be referred to medicinal therapies
      if they are not "on track" to reach their blood pressure goal. The patient is considered on track if any of the following are true:
    </p>
    <ul>
      <li>They have no active BP goal, so their progress cannot be determined.</li>
      <li>They don't have a BP set, so whether the goal has been met cannot be determined.</li>
      <li>The goal has been met.</li>
      <li>They have been working toward their goal for less than 3 months.</li>
    </ul>
    <br/>

    <h3>Diagnosis</h3>
    <img height="500" src="dxLogic.PNG" alt="Diagnosis Logic"/>
    <br/>

    <h3>Monitoring</h3>
    <img height="500" src="monitorLogic.PNG" alt="Monitoring Logic"/>
    <br/>

    <h3>Lifestyle Changes</h3>
    <img height="500" src="lifestyleLogic.PNG" alt="Lifestyle Intervention Logic"/>
    <br/>

    <h3>Pharmacologic Intervention</h3>
    <img height="500" src="drugLogic.PNG" alt="Medication Logic"/>
    <br/>

    <h3>Adverse Events</h3>
    <img height="500" src="adverseLogic.PNG" alt="Adverse Event Logic"/>

</div>
