<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../input-cache/schemas/R5/fhir-single.xsd">
    <a name="top" />
    <h3>Monitoring of Already Diagnosed Patient Workflow</h3>

    <img height="500" src="flow-monitoring.png" alt="Monitoring of Already Diagnosed Patient Workflow diagram"/>

    <p>If a patient who has a diagnosis of hypertension accesses this tool, this workflow will run.</p>

    <p>First, the tool checks to see if the patient has a current blood pressure goal. If the patient does not, it sets a default goal of &lt;140/90 mmHg and checks to see if the patient would like to adjust that goal. The tool will then check whether it can find a complete set of blood pressure readings. If it cannot, it will recommend taking additional blood pressure readings either at home or in a clinical setting.</p>

    <p>If either all blood pressure readings or the set of blood pressures averages greater than 140/90 mmHg, the tool will recommend that the patient begin both pharmacologic and non-pharmacologic treatment to control their blood pressure. These are separate workflows.</p>

    <p>If the set of blood pressure readings are above the patient’s goal, the tool will recommend that the patient begin non-pharmacologic treatment. If blood pressure remains above goal after three months of non-pharmacologic treatment, the tool will then recommend beginning pharmacologic treatment.</p>

    <p>If blood pressure is below goal, the tool will recommend ongoing monitoring but no further recommendations will be provided unless changes in blood pressure are detected.</p>

    <a name="links" />
    <h3>Links</h3>

    <ul>
        <li><a href="https://www.heart.org/en/health-topics/high-blood-pressure/understanding-blood-pressure-readings">AHA: Understanding Blood Pressure Readings</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/files/docs/public/heart/hbp_low.pdf">NIH: Controlling Blood Pressure</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/32773652/">Bell 2021: Potential for overdiagnosis and underdiagnosis because of blood pressure variability</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://my.clevelandclinic.org/health/diagnostics/16330-24-hour-ambulatory-blood-pressure-monitoring">Cleveland Clinic: Understanding 24-hour monitoring</a></li>
    </ul>

</div>
