<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../input-cache/schemas/R5/fhir-single.xsd">
  <!-- The spaces between the open and close "a" tag are mandatory.  (Cuz HTML renderers are dumb...) -->
  <a name="intro" />
  <h3>Introduction</h3>
	<p>
    This implementation guide provides the decision logic for a patient-facing FHIR-based Clinical Decision Support (CDS) tool developed at
      Oregon Health &amp; Science University (OHSU) for the treatment of High Blood Pressure (Hypertension). This work was funded by the Agency for Healthcare
      Research and Quality (AHRQ) under a two-year U18 grant.
  </p>
  <a href="PcHTN_1pager.pdf"> Research summary and one-page project overview</a>

  <p>
    This implementation guide was developed to identify commonalities between clinical practice guidelines (CPG) for hypertension treatment.
    Based on these guidelines, and with input from expert collaborators and from surveys and interviews of primary care providers and
    hypertensive patients, we developed the decision logic for this CDS tool. Our goal in developing this tool is to improve patient
    outcomes by improving adherence to hypertension CPGs, facilitating patient education about hypertension, improving shared decision
    making by providing CPG-adherent treatment recommendations, and by incorporating patient preferences into the decision logic.
  </p>

	<a name="technical" />
	<h3>Technical Overview</h3>
	<p>
    This implementation guide utilizes the Clinical Quality Language (CQL) development language. This is a human readable HL7 authoring language
      designed to facilitate harmonizing standards used for electronic clinical quality measures (eCQMs) and CDS. Each of the component parts is
      represented by a CQL artifact that checks entered data against value sets for hypertension and related conditions to select which treatment
      recommendations should be provided to end-users, based on identified patient preferences and patient context.
  </p>
  <a name="walkthrough" />
  <p>
    - The main sections of this IG are:<br/>
    - Diagnosis<br/>
    - Screening<br/>
    - Non-Pharmacologic Treatment<br/>
    - Pharmacologic Treatment<br/>
    - Adverse Event Response
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>
      <a href="background.html">Background</a> - provides business context for the implementation guide and information that implementers should be
      familiar with before reading the remainder of the IG.  There could be multiple pages for this.
    </li>
    <li>
      <a href="spec.html">Detailed Specification</a> - The actual stuff implementers are expected to do.  (Could be multiple pages for this.)
    </li>
    <li>
      <a href="downloads.html">Downloads</a> - Allows downloading a copy of this implementation guide and other useful information
    </li>
  </ul>

  <a name="references" />
  <h3>References and Disclaimers</h3>

  <p>
    This product uses publicly available data courtesy of the U.S. National Library of Medicine (NLM),
    National Institutes of Health, Department of Health and Human Services; NLM is not responsible for
    the product and does not endorse or recommend this or any other product.
  </p>

  <p>
    Alper BS, Price A, van Zuuren EJ, Fedorowicz Z, Shaughnessy AF, Oettgen P, Elwyn G, Qaseem A, Kunnamo I, Gupta U, Carter DD, Mittelman M, Berg-Nelson C, Mayer M. <br/>
    Consistency of Recommendations for Evaluation and Management of Hypertension. JAMA Netw Open. 2019 Nov 1;2(11):e1915975. doi: 10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2019.15975. <br/>
    PMID: 31755945; PMCID: PMC6902818.<br/>
    <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6902818/">Full text</a>
  </p>

</div>